丛林奇航  翻译:麦尼芽
所有的传说都来自真实故事
All legends are born in truth.
亚马逊河上流传着一个传说
From the Amazon
关于"月亮之泪"的一种花
came the legend of the Tears of the Moon.
据说一片花瓣
A single petal from the great Tree
可以根治百疾，可以打破所有诅咒
could cure any illness and break any curse.
几个世纪以来
Over the centuries,
无数个探险队深入密林
many expeditions went searching
寻找能够开出月亮之泪的治愈神树
for the Healing Tears of legend.
其中最著名的
None more famous
是来自西班牙的征服者-唐·洛佩德·阿吉雷
than that of the conquistador, Don Lope de Aguirre,
他发誓要将这种力量据为己有
who was determined to possess the Tears' power.
但是大自然不允许他这么做
But the jungle protected the Tears.
历史或许会告诉你，他的探险以失败告终
History will tell you, his journey ended in failure.
但是传说并没有在这里结束
But legend tells more.
神树守护族人发现了他
That he was found by the Guardians of the Tree
将他从死亡边缘救了回来
and nursed back to life.
但他开始向族人索要"圣镞"
That he demanded they give him the sacred Arrowhead,
一个找到月亮之泪的关键
the key to finding the Tears of the Moon.
当阿吉雷的露出獠牙时
That Aguirre attacked.
丛林俘虏了他们
But the jungle defended,
阿吉雷和他的爪牙被拖入密林深处
and Aguirre and his conquistadors were taken,
永世不得踏出诅咒之河
cursed, never to leave sight of the river again,
永世不得超生
unable to leave or die...
至少传说是这样说的
...or so the legend goes.
"我们知道队伍消失于"
"We know they disappeared here,
"哭泣水晶"
"in the region of Lagrimas de Cristal,
"我们将在这里探求到传说的真相"
"and it is here that we will find the true source of the legend,
"一棵具有无与伦比的治疗能力的神树"
"a tree that possesses unparalleled healing powers.
"我尊敬的同事们..."
"My esteemed colleagues..."
"我向你们保证"
"...I assert that the famous legend
"月亮之泪不是神话"
"of the Tears of the Moon is not a myth
"而是有科学根据的事实"  -而是有科学根据的事实
"but scientific truth."  -...but scientific truth.
"这将在现代医学界掀起革命"
"One that could revolutionizemodern medicine,
"在城市和战场上"
"curing illnesses that not only scourge our cities,
"治疗无数能够夺人性命的恶疾"
"but cut down more of our soldiers in the trenches than German bullets.
"我此行目的是希望获得贵协会的封存文物的许可"
"I have come here today to request access to your exclusive archives..."
-"包括那个古老的圣镞"
-"...including an ancient Arrowhead
"据传已经被瀑布探险队寻获"
"recently recovered from
the lost expedition of Dr. Albert Falls.
"圣镞也许就是那"
"The Arrowhead represents
the missing piece
"解开月亮之泪位置的"
"that will finally unlock the location
"这里停顿一下，比较有戏剧效果"
"of, pause for dramatic effect, the..."
"最后一块拼图"
"The Tears of the Moon."
我想你表达得很清楚了，霍顿先生
And you made your request, Mr. Houghton,
我们的回覆是，戏剧性的强调一下
and the answer remains, emphatically,
"没门儿"  -同意 同意
"no."  -MEN: Hear, hear.
我们的收藏是为合法的学术家提供的
Our archives are the providence of legitimate scholars,
不是某个心血来潮的外行人  -同意 同意
not inspired amateurs.  -MEN: Hear, hear.
话虽如此，既然我已经站在台上了
Be that as it may, since I have your attention,
可以让...请允许我解释...
would you at least allow me to, uh, continue with my, uh,
研究指出，可能...
examination of how important
"月亮之泪 "对医学很重要?
the Tears of the Moon could be to medicine?
你好 -哈啰
Hello.  -Hello.
沙卡・祖鲁
Shaka Zulu. -Yes.
他利用简单的改造
Through one simple act of innovation,
便压制了所有敌人...
he came to dominate all his enemies from the...
不仅如此，还有包围战术
There was that, but also the encirclement tactic.
你不该出现在这里
You are not where you ought to be.
哦 对..我想我...
Yes. You're right. Uh, I think I...
秘书台往那边走
The secretaries' gallery is that way.
真谢谢您
Thank you so much.
是一个可以治疗各种疾病..
A cure for all ailments,
不管是体虚
whether it be consumption,
白喉、登革热
diphtheria, dengue fever,
黄热病、花粉热， 热 热...
yellow fever, hay fever, fever fever...
各种热，恩 都能因此康复
All fevers, um, would be covered.
不好意思
Excuse me.
是?
Yes?
此区仅限协会成员
This area is for Society members only.
是吗?  -是的
Is it? -Yes.
哦，我很抱歉
Oh, I'm so sorry about that.
不过坦白说，我不知道你到底是怎么进...
Well, to be quite frank, I've no idea how you even...
霍顿先生，我们允许你来
Mr. Houghton, we granted you an audience
是看在你已故父亲的面子上
in deference to your late father.
但是我得说，这听起来很像是某位女士写的论文
This, however, seems remarkably like a paper
我有幸亲自退稿
I had the honor of refusing when it was submitted by a female writer,
莉莉.霍顿博士
a Dr. Lily Houghton.
应该无关 对吧?
No relation, I take it?
当然没有
None that I've ever agreed to.
要我送你出去吗?
Shall we help you find your way out?
"瀑布远征队"。
它保存在那边的箱子里
It's in the first crate of the lot.
非常感谢你的慷慨捐献
And thank you so much for your very generous contribution,
特别是这些纯金条
in solid gold bars, I might add.
如果每个人都这样付钱该有多好
Would make life so much simpler if more people paid in gold.
我只想要箱子里的一件东西
I don't want the whole lot, just one thing.
看来有人先我们一步
Seems someone got to it before me.
呃，应该没有，我确定所有东西都在里面。
Um, they shouldn't have. I'm sure it's all there.
一定是滑出来掉在某处..
It must have just slid somewhere.
我 我找一下
Let's... Let's see.
肯定在这..
It was definitely there.
阻止她!  -噢!
-Stop her! -Oh!
嗨，介绍一下，这是一把"恩古尼鱼叉"
Hello. I just wanted you to know, this is a Nguni assegai.
标签贴成 "祖鲁了"
It's been mislabeled as "Zulu."
抓住她!
Grab her!
噢
Oh.
别跑!
Wait!
轨道的尽头了，下来!
The end of the line. Get down!
噢 妈呀  -不 不 不!!
Oh, my God! -No, no, no!
祝您有美好的一天
Good day, sir!
你以为你是第一个赶走我的人吗？
You think you're the first to eject me?
比那些拒绝过我欧洲俱乐部差多了！
I have been turned out of some of the best clubs in Europe!
天啊！
Oh, my gosh!
弗莱恩，把盒子给我，我会帮你起来
Fraulein, give me that box and I will help you up.
停下！停下！  -你快抓不住了
-Stop! Stop!  -You are slipping!
票钱，谢谢
CONDUCTOR: Fare, please.
我可以赊账吗？
Can I put it on a tab?
同胞们准备出发了吗?
You shipping out, lads?
我代表皇家人类学探险协会...
I think I speak for the entire Society
向你表示最诚挚的歉意
when I offer my most sincere apologies
挖金王子
to you, Prince Joachim.
你刚才讲出了我的名字
You just told them my name.
噢
Oh.
是约阿席王子
It is Prince "Joachim."
约阿席
Joachim.
很好 -约阿席王子
Good. -Now, Prince Joachim,
我们可以退还您的钱...
we could refund your money from the...
钱留着，但是你要告诉我
You keep that money, and you tell me,
那女人是谁
who is that woman?
我不
I don't...
我不知道那是谁
I do know who that was.
侵入私宅 偷窃
Breaking and entering, grand larceny,
最糟的是，竟然坐公车离开?
and worst of all, forced to take public transport.
我该担心你吗？
Should I be concerned about you?
你怎么这么说，麦桂格？
Why would you say that, MacGregor?
那可是能拯救无数生命，改变世界的花瓣
This is a petal that could heal all, save countless lives, change the world.
你不是一直梦想着冒险吗？
Haven't you been dreaming about another adventure?
如果想去一个原始又落后
If I wanted to go to a primitive backwater
语言不通鸡里瓜啦的地方
where I can't understand a word anyone's saying,
去苏格兰不就好了吗
I'd visit our relatives in Scotland.
那次和父亲去不丹的可怕旅行是我的恶梦
Barely got over that hideous trip with Father to Bhutan.
你才少两根脚趾而已
You only lost two toes.
我当时才七岁  -那你就留在这吧
I was seven. -Then just stay here.
你留下 你就待家里
You can. You can just stay here.
不用担心 我就单枪匹马去亚马逊雨林
Don't worry about me. All alone, in the Amazon.
那谁来照顾你？
But who'd look after you?
恩 不知道
Well, I have no idea.
拜托 振作一下
Come on, cheer up.
坐轮船到巴西，换铁路到波尔多维洛...
Steamer to Brazil, rail to Porto Velho...
我们会在那里找到船长
...then all we need is a skipper.
首先，恭喜各位
First of all, let me congratulate you
选择了一位非常优秀的船长
on your excellent choice of skipper.
在所有能进入雨林的船当中
Of all the jungle cruises you could take in the Amazon,
本船无疑是
this one is undoubtedly
最便宜的
the cheapest.
也是最刺激的
But also the most thrilling.
你还在导览吗？
Are you still giving a tour?
有阿 我正在解说
Yes, I am.
可以退费吗?  -不可以
Perhaps a refund? -No refunds.
亲爱的 早告诉你 搭别艘渡轮
We should've taken the other cruise, honey. Told you.
船长!
Skipper!
船长?
Skipper?
船长! 你需要看看这个!
Skipper! I think you should see this!
小心 要通过了
Heads up! Coming through!
我们到哪了？  -到鬼门关前了
Where were we? -About to die.
啊
Ah.
船长!
Skipper!
先生?
Sir?
这钮扣怎么一直卡住
Sometimes these buttons get stuck.
船长!
Skipper!
好了
All right.
各位往左看，有一些顽皮的大嘴鸟
If you look to the left of the boat, you'll see some very playful toucans.
正在玩它们最爱的"大嘴摔角"游戏
They're playing their favorite game of beak-wrestling.
这游戏的缺点是
The only drawback is,
只有二嘴鸟能玩
only two can play.
有二只鸟 二只都是大嘴鸟
There's two birds, and those are toucans.
我意思是只有"二只"大嘴鸟能玩
I'm saying that only "two can" play.
一二三四的二，是"二只" "大嘴"鸟能玩
Not one, but "two can" play.
哇
Wow.
现在你们眼前的石头叫做砂岩
The rocks you see here in the river are sandstone.
有些人也叫它花岗岩
But some people just take them for granite.
这是我的私藏"巨石"景点之一
It's one of my boulder attractions.
各位可知 我曾经在一家果汁厂当过罐头工
You know, before this, I used to work in an orange juice factory,
直到我拿了个罐头 (直到有次喝醉)
but I got canned.
噢... -却榨不出来  (没法集中注意力)
Oh...  -Couldn't concentrate.
噢...
Oh...
然后他们就把给一起我榨了
Yeah, they put the squeeze on me, too.
这笑话真赞，我应该用这开场的
That's a good one. I should've opened with that one.
各位可知，那只大蟒蛇据说
You know, they say the boa constrictor right there is capable
每顿饭能吃掉200多公斤
of eating up to 500 pounds per sitting.
我个人认为，我没办法
Personally, I find that very hard...
一次吃掉200多公斤
to swallow.
妈咪，你能不能让叔叔安静？
Mommy, can you please make him stop?
不可以! 插嘴不乖
No one can. And don't interrupt me like that again.
小心我把你抓去给大蟒蟒当晚餐
I will feed you to the boa.
她只是个孩子
She is a small child.
它最爱吃小孩子
He loves small children.
嘴巴闭起来
Close your mouth.
嘿 嘿
Hey! Hey!
不要乱碰  雨林可是危机四伏
Hands in the boat! Know this about the jungle,
举凡所见之物都会要你的命
everything that you see wants to kill you.
轻而易举
And can.
有超毒"天使号角"(曼陀罗)
Poison angel's trumpet.
马钱子 箭毒 香蕉蜘蛛
Strychnos. Curare. Banana spider.
埋葬那些死于食肉猛兽、疾病，再也找不到青春之泉的人
Marauders, dead of fever, for never finding the Fountain of Youth.
埋葬着寻找黄金之城的探险家 死于被黄貂鱼蜇伤
Adventurers, stung by stingrays, searching for cities of gold.
埋葬着因为残害当地土著而被诅咒的入侵者
Conquistadors, cursed, for slaughtering innocent natives.
那里有个才刚被
And then there's the ones that just got eaten
史前夺命河马吃掉的
by the deadly hippopotamus.
但河马不是这里的原生...
But hippos aren't native to the...
嘘!
Shh.
看!
Look out!
准备迎接我最爱的部分，丛林的鬼斧神工之作
This is the highlight of the tour. It's my favorite part of the jungle.
女士先生们，准备好了吗
Ladies and gentlemen, get ready
世界第八大奇迹
for the eighth Wonder of the World.
看好...
Wait for it...
水之屁股！
The backside of water!
看起来跟水的前面一样啊
It looks just like the front side.
完全不一样啊
It's completely different.
世界第八大奇迹，水之屁股
It's the eighth Wonder of the World, the backside of water.
朋友们，拿出你的相机 拜托 你不想错过这个的
Guys, get your cameras out, come on. You don't wanna miss this.
喀擦 喀擦 喀擦
Snap, snap, snap.
别停
Keep snapping.
希望那不是普卡米丘纳，南半球最血腥的蛮族
I hope those aren't the Puka Michuna, the deadliest hunters in the hemisphere.
他们吃人
They hunt humans!
别这样
Come on.
可以开快点吗
Please, go faster.
哦，太快引擎会坏，我买不起新的
Oh, any faster would damage my engine, and I can't afford a new one.
感谢
Grazie.
免客气
Prego.
来，听好，你们都付过钱了
All right, listen up, I get paid by the number of people I take out,
死了与我无关 所以抓紧了
not by the number of people I bring back. Hold on!
啊你，呃，顾好行李
Ah. Be a good chap and, uh, take care of the luggage.
说过别穿长裤
Told you not to wear trousers.
徒增路人注意
Drawing unnecessary attention.
我才不在乎
I don't care in the slightest.
哈啰
Hello.
大家 你们今天表现得很棒
Well, folks, you were all outstanding today,
现在请离开，回去码头
now I need you all out, standing on the dock.
意思是"滚下船"，认真的
That means "get off my boat."  I'm only serious.
叔叔再见
Au revoir.
女士 别忘了
Ma'am, don't forget
行李  -谢谢
to collect your baggage. -Thank you.
骗你的 它在后面
I'm only kidding. He's behind you.
再见
Adios.
记得照顾一下札克，他是个好孩子
Make sure you take care of Zaqueu, he's a good kid.
看起来只有10岁 其实47岁了 谢谢
He looks 10, but he's secretly 47. Thank you, sir.
哇 好迷人，这些是你做的吗?
Look, how stunning. Did you make these?
太美了
Beautiful.
哦，这很不优，不好意思，我觉得你...
Oh, that is awful. Excuse me, I just think that you...
就...别和猴商大小声了
Let's not start a fight with a monkey vendor.
不是我想吵架，是猴子不该被关在笼子里
I'm not going to start a fight. They clearly shouldn't be in cages.
喔买尬，看!是我们的船，那里!那里!
Oh, my gosh! Look, there's the boats! Look, look, look!
我觉得我们该帮自己订个好房间，吃一餐好的
Right. I think we've earned ourselves some nice lunch at the hotel,
泡个热水澡同时小酌一番
then a bath and a cocktail.
我们跨越大半个地球不是为了泡澡和小酌
We did not travel half the globe for baths and cocktails.
得找到尼罗先生才能确保行程顺利 快来
We must find this Mr. Nilo and secure our travel. Come on!
法兰克欠我钱
Frank owes me money.
早安啊 法兰小弟
Buongiorno, Frankie boy!
别这样叫
Please don't call me that.
嘿 法兰小弟 知道今天什么日子?
Hey, Frankie, you know what today is?
法兰克还钱日
Frank owes me money.
今天是本月的第三个星期二
It's the third Tuesday of the month.
还钱 法兰克 钱
My money, Frank. My contante.
在哪
Where is it?
哦，你是说这些钱? 都在这儿了
Oh, you mean this money? It's all here.
我这星期的饭钱只需要一点点
I just need this, so I can finally eat this week.
剩下的全都给你
The rest e per te.
别看不起我 法兰克 我的钱不只这些
You insult me, Frank. This is not all of my money.
连我的脚趾缝都不够填
This is like a little pinky toe, nothing...
我的小脚趾拇指头都不够塞 法兰克
Itty-bitty, little nothing of my money, Frank.
借了我的钱买新引擎
You borrow money from me to get a new engine,
就该连本带利还来
well, you got to pay me back, plus interest.
是的 我要扣押你的引擎了
Yeah, I'm going to keep your engine for now.
一周内还我5000元，你就能赎回去
I get 5,000 real in one week, then you get it back.
一星期内不给钱，我就没收你整条船
I don't get my money in one week, then I keep your whole boat.
你要我船干啥
What do you want my boat for?
你有一堆好船了啊
You have nice boats. You have all the boats.
还没 法兰克 但我打赌
Not yet, I don't, Frank. But I bet you I will.
你下星期一定会还钱
I'm gonna guess, by next week.
后会有期 法兰小弟
Arrivederci, Franco.
呃 这什么鬼地方
Ugh, what fresh hell is this?
喔 我爱上这里了
Oh, I love it!
不好意思
Excuse me, um,
请问您知道尼罗先生
do you know Mr. Nilo...
真优雅
Classy clientele.
到家了 罗西塔
Home again, Rosita.
亲亲
Mmm.
嘿
Hey!
也许得去别处找尼罗先生了
Perhaps I should search for Mr. Nilo elsewhere.
听说永远能在旅馆吧台找到他
There's always a chance he's at the hotel bar.
好吧 动作快点，不然我自己先走
Fine. But be quick about it or I'll leave without you.
哦，这个选项越来越可行了
Oh, that option is becoming increasingly desirable.
不好意思
Excuse me.
恩，请问尼罗先生的办公室?
Um, Mr. Nilo's office?
楼上  -谢谢，谢谢(葡萄牙文)
Upstairs. Thank you. Obri... Obrigada.
最近怎么样啊
How you doing?
尼罗先生? 您好?
Mr. Nilo? Hello?
法兰克欠债
Frank owes me money.
啊，你在呢，我正想和你谈笔生意
Ah, there you are. I was hoping we might have a small business chat.
现在没空
Not a good chat time right now.
但如果你明早再来
But if you came back first thing tomorrow morning,
我很有空
lots of available chat then.
不 我想要现在
No, I would much prefer now.
我是莉莉霍顿博士
My name is Dr. Lily Houghton,
我跟我弟打算渡河
and my brother and are looking for passage upriver,
有人说你是唯一能安全渡河的男人
and I'm told that you are the man for the job.
你被唬烂了  -不可能 你..
You were told wrong. -That's impossible, because you come...
...明明榜上有名
...highly recommended.
我有个想法: 你走开
I have an idea. Please go away.
尼罗先生，外面的船上到处都是你的名字
Mr. Nilo, your name is plastered all over the boats outside.
我觉得你在无理取闹
I think you're being a bit unreasonable.
明明是你在撬我的门
You're the one trying to break down my door.
我钱很多
I have a lot of money.
噢
Oh.
你衣着真特别  -有人这么说过了
You're insistent. -It's been said.
我们要逆河而上，朝着秘鲁安第斯山脉的方向
Now, we're headed upriver, in the direction of the Peruvian Andes.
这地区不会出现在一般地图上
This region doesn't really have a name on the conventional map,
但有些人知道
but it was once known to some
这个区域叫做"哭泣水晶"
as Lagrimas de Cristal.
你穿着裤子耶
You're wearing pants.
长裤，是的，跟你一样
Trousers. And yes, as are you.
英国的女人现在都这么潮吗
Do women in England do that now?
这个嘛 我们现在好像不在英国吧
Well, we're not in England, last time I checked.
看，跟裤子一样令人震惊的是...
Now, look, as shocking as the pants are, I'd really...
法兰克 把我的钱给我
ROSITA: Frank owes me money.
Frank owes me money.
法兰克欠钱不还
请你一杯?   -法兰克是谁?
Can I get you a drink? -Who's Frank?
谁知道  -我想喝一点东西
I have no idea.  -I will have a little something.
雪碧?     -你想的到的我都有
Spritzer, I assume?  -I'll have whatever you're having.
那 尼罗先生，你熟悉那个地区吗?
So, do you know the region, Mr. Nilo?
这个嘛 亚马逊河就像我的家
Well, if it's on the Amazon River, I know it.
只是小姐，我得告诉你
And, lady, I could tell you,
地球上什么地方都能去
of all the places in the world you can go,
就这个"哭泣水晶"不能去
the last place you wanna go is Lagrimas de Cristal.
喔 但我要 我也会去
Oh, but I do. And I will.
不 你不能，长裤
Oh, but you won't, Pants.
你到不了 没人到的了
You can't get there. Nobody can get there.
即使可以 也没人想，这不是度假
And if they could, they wouldn't. It's not a fun vacation.
我不是来度假的
Well, I'm not here for a vacation.
你从哪里拿到这张地图的?
Where'd you get the map?
很了不起对吧? 多仔细的标记
Isn't it extraordinary? The detail and the care he took.
出自阿吉雷的制图师之手
It was drawn by Aguirre's cartographer.
后来传到我父亲手上，他在我小时候
And it belonged to my father, who used to tell me
告诉了我月亮之泪的传说
all about the Tears of the Moon when I was a little girl.
所以...这就是你的动机? 你爸的床边故事?
So, that's why you wanna go? Your daddy's bedtime stories?
听着 你到底能不能带我们去那?
Look, can you get us there or not?
还是我浪费了一堆时间跟你拐弯抹角?
Or has this just been a colossal waste of my time?
我可以带你去
I could get you there,
但你得小心登革热
but you have to consider the dengue fever,
史前巨蟒 还有
anaconda, plus,
还有 危险的普卡米丘纳人
look, lady, that's the home of the actual Puka Michuna.
他们生吃人 再挖出你的眼珠子串成项链
They're the ones that like to eat you and wear your eyes for beads.
听着，女士，我得实话实说，还是做一些安全的事情吧
Look, lady, I gotta be honest with you, let's do something that's safe.
我 你 和你的裤子
So, me, you, and your pants,
可以游览小镇，很有趣的
we can go for a ride around town. That'd be fun.
带你去看瀑布 你感觉就很喜欢瀑布
I'll show you some waterfalls. You look like you like waterfalls.
还可以带你去看
And I'll also show you
刚刚发现的侏儒象群
the herd of pygmy elephants we just found.
我们去看大象吧
Let's go see some elephants.
我的钥匙丢了     -你搞丢了?
I lost my key for that thing. -Did you?
掉河里了
I did.
那看来是行不通的
Well, that's never gonna do it.
你会伤到自己 那很尖喔
You're gonna hurt yourself. Those are very sharp.
尼罗先生，我和德里的扒手
Mr. Nilo, I spent my childhood playtime
一起长大的，所以...
with the toddler pickpockets of Delhi, so...
有了
There we go.
不介意的话，我会顾好自身安全
Allow me to manage my own safety, if that's all right.
现在可以谈价钱了吗?
Now, shall we negotiate a price?
还是我另寻他船?
Or shall I just cast about for another skipper?
谁要买单?
Who's paying for all this?
哦，尼罗先生请客
Oh, Mr. Nilo insisted it was his treat.
没错
That's right.
我顶多出5,000
I consider 5,000 real more than adequate.
10,000，亲自带你去，我可是最棒的船长
10,000, I take you there myself. I am my best captain.
你最谦虚 我懂
Oh, and your most modest. Fine, 10,000.
10,000 带你活着过去
10,000 to bring you there alive.
另外 15,000 帮你把尸体带回家
If I have to bring you back dead, it's 15,000.
为什么我死了更贵?
Why should I pay more dead?
我要背你啊小姐 尸体不会自己走路
Dead, I'd have to carry you. Dead's a lot harder, lady.
来回 20,000 不论死活
20, dead or alive.
成交 但是要全额现金
Okay, but I get paid in full
在到达目的地前折返的时后付款
when we turn back before Lagrimas de Cristal.
为什么要折返
Why ever would we be turning back?
你一看到激流就会跪着求我回头
Well, you're gonna beg me to turn back, first sign of the rapids.
来啊 我很期待
Well, I look forward to disappointing you.
莉莉 看我找到了谁
Lily, look who I found at the hotel bar.
啊 尼罗船长!
Ah! Mr. Nilo.
早安 女士
Buongiorno, signorina.
他很会讨价还价，可惜遇到我
He drives a hard bargain, but he met his match with me.
我们五万成交
Negotiated him down to 50,000.
这位朋友是谁?
Who's your friend?
非尼罗
Not Mr. Nilo.
非尼罗  非尼罗
Not Mr. Nilo, no. -No.
那你应该是...?
So, I suppose that would make you...
好好享用 法兰克
Enjoying your meal, Frank?
是那个"欠钱不还"的法兰克?
As in, "Frank owes me money," Frank?
原来如此 都合理了
Of course. It's all making perfect sense.
我要是真信你 那可真是冤大头了
I suppose it's only a scam if you fall for it.
谢啰，法兰克先生，永远不见
Well, thank you, Mr. Frank. I hope we never meet again.
嗨 尼罗先生
Mr. Nilo, hello.
你刚吹我口哨?    -一万二
Did you just whistle at me? -12,000.
呃，对不起
Eh, scusa.
10,000   -你不是搞丢了钥匙?
10,000. -Aren't you missing an engine?
女士，他连外面的茅坑都没法带你过去
Signorina, he could not get you as far as the outhouse.
其实 他的船就像个茅坑
In fact, his boat kind of looks like an outhouse.
拉奎娜号是港口最快的船，有最干净的厕所
You're never gonna find a faster boat in the harbor than La Quila.
有如刚出浴的凤凰
Plus, she has the finest bath in all Brazil.
为何要相信你?
Why should I trust you?
因为我是唯一能带你安全到达的男人
I'm the only one that could get you there.
喔买尬
Oh, my gosh!
小心 它们能闻到恐惧气味
Careful. They can smell fear.
我没在怕
I am not afraid.
我怕，我裤子一阵温热
Might be me. Warm, liquid fear.
Shoo.
大家都冷静下来
Everybody stay calm!
又漏了一点出来  -闭嘴
A little bit more fear just came out.  -Shut up!
痛..
Ouch.
他做到了!
He did it!
谢谢大家
Thank you, thank you. Thank you.
欢迎来到弗兰克沃夫的丛林之旅
Frank Wolff. Jungle Navigation.
镇里评分最高，百分百不怕猎豹
Best rates in town, completely jaguar-free.
我不管你个人的事
You are a lot of things that I don't really care for.
只是你勉强可以胜任，所以...
But you are capable, so,
12,000.
-15,000.
-12,000.
-15...
-Nuh!
12,000. 一半现付，一半活着回来再付
12. Half now, half upon return, alive,
如果你说好，我就在码头等你
and if we have a deal, I'll meet you at the docks with our luggage.
-成交   -很好
-We have a deal. -Good.
拉奎娜一早就会在港口准备启航
La Quila will be ready first thing in the morning.
不，欠钱仔，我们10分钟后出发
Oh, no, "Frank owes me money," we're gonna depart in 10 minutes.
不 两小时后天就黑了
No, it gets dark in two hours.
你想取消吗？
Does it?
我们将在10分钟内出发
We should probably leave in 10 minutes.
选的好
Good decision.
不是现在
Not now.
我说 不是现在
I said, not now.
来来来
Come here.
好乖，普西玛 好姑娘
You did good, Proxima. You're a good girl.
有点迟到，咬太用力，但是
You were a little late, and you bit me way too hard.
还是干的好
But you did good.
你要在丛林里开化装舞会?
Jungle doesn't care how pretty your dresses are,
别把所有家当带上船
you're never gonna get all your luggage on my boat.
不是我的
Not mine.
是我的 我保证
Mine. And, I assure you,
这里每个物品对我的存活都至关重要
every one of these items is entirely necessary for my survival.
真棒 有了这些冗余的重量
Well, with all this extra added weight,
我们永远都无法离开港口 所以 拿走
we'd be lucky to even get out of the harbor, so, no.
不穿晚礼服吃晚餐就不叫晚餐，对不对?
Dinner without a dinner jacket is hardly, well, dinner, is it?
接招
Now...
靠你啰
be a good chap.
你要怎么处理这些鸟
What're you gonna do with those birds?
打包起来送去巴黎
We're gonna stuff them and send them to Paris.
不
No, you're not.
你...你在做什么?
What on Earth do you think you're doing?
嘿  麦桂格
Hey!  MacGregor!
给我捡回来喔
That will need to be retrieved immediately.
帮个忙 麦桂格
Help, MacGregor!
麦桂格!
MacGregor!
不
No.
那是我的网球拍耶
Those are my tennis rackets.
现在是漂流木了
It's a river cruise.
日装和鞋子?  -丢了
Assorted day wear and shoes? -No.
小说和泳装?
Light reading and bathing costumes?
丢了
Good.
酒?    -我们会需要它
The liquor?    -That one can stay.
给我停下，你这个四肢发达头脑简单的小丑
Now, listen here, you buffoon,
如果你再扔掉这些东西...
if you scuttle any more of my luggage, I will...
天啊 你有好多肌肉
Gosh, there's a lot of you, isn't there?
巨不巨    -莉莉?
Yeah, there is. -Lily?
莉莉?
Lily?
嘿
Hey!
他启动引擎了  -喔 我们该走了
Nilo! He's got your engine! -Oh, we gotta go.
我的妹妹
Not without my sister.
拿好你的东西 快走
Come on. Get your stuff. Let's go.
女士
Lady!
我们走吧
Let's go.
没有沐浴乳我死也不走
I am not leaving without my toiletries.
熄火!
Shut down that engine!
欧 该走了
Okay, time to leave.
为什么要追我们?
Why are they chasing us?
我也很莫名其妙
I have no idea.
是个女人，把钱给我
Here's the English woman. Pay up.
莉莉
Lily.
急转右舷 维持航向
Turn starboard. Resume heading.
虾米? 啥么意思？
What?  I don't know what that means.
小姐...
Lady, look, we gotta...
喔 法兰克 对不起
Oh, God, sorry, Frank.
没关系 拳够硬
It's all right. Strong form.
跟着我 法兰克
Frank, follow me.
别往上爬 往这边
Don't go up there. It's that way.
小姐 这个方向才对
Lady, it's that way.
不要管猴子了，他们很快乐
Lady! Leave the monkeys. The monkeys are fine.
别往上
Don't go up there.
小姐 别跑了!    -现在不是时候 法兰克
Lady, stop! -Not now, Frank!
还好吗 长裤小姐?
How you doing, Pants?
我很好
I'm good.
你知道，我一直想告诉你...
You know, I was trying to tell you about the...
我知道  -来吧
I know. -Come on.
不
No.
跳  妹子 跳
Come on! Lady, jump!
还在等什么
What are you waiting for?
发现他们了！
There they are!
-莉莉呢? -那里
-Where's Lily? -There.
又来了
Of course she is.
来吧，来吧
Okay. Come on, lady.
在镇上逛街逛到迷路了?
Tucking in a spot of sightseeing?
欢迎回来，伙计
How nice of you to join us.
干嘛不跳河?
Why didn't you jump in the water?
我不想谈论这话题   -她不会游泳
I don't wanna talk about it.  -She can't swim.
所以你租了一艘船 然后怕水
You booked a river cruise, and you can't swim?
我对游泳不感兴趣
I have no intention of swimming.
那20个壮汉又是怎么回事
And what about the 20 guys chasing us around town?
我不知道，也许他们对什么感兴趣
I may or may not have something in my possession that
也许我有他们感兴趣的东西
may or may not be of interest to other interested parties.
-Shh!
我知道她在你眼皮子底下溜走，克塞尔
I assume she escaped your grasp, Axel.
是的，阁下
Yes, your excellency.
然后我会帮你收烂摊子
Then I'll take care of it myself.
神树是带领德国打胜仗的关键
The Tree is the key to Germany winning this war.
圣镞则是带领我们找到神树的关键
The Arrowhead will show us the way to the Tree.
不能让它离开港口
We cannot let it leave this harbor.
上浮!
Surface!
那些家伙是谁?    -天啊
Who are those guys? -Oh, my gosh.
我要涨价了
The price just went up.
别这样
Come on!
怎么了   -船失去动力了
What happened? -We lost all power.
重新上弹
Reload!
你得帮我掌舵
I need you to take the wheel.
不不不，交给我 我是优秀的司机
No, no, no. I am an excellent driver.
说的就是你 我们唯一的希望
Anyone but you.
记得急转右舷
Starboard.
在他们重新上膛之前
Quick, before he reloads.  -You missed...
是的，船长
Understood.
交给你了  -欧 谢天谢地
It's all yours. -Oh, thank God!
你偷我引擎?
You steal my engine?
滚离我的码头
Get off my dock!
这是私人港口，法兰克，你彻底完了
It's private property, Frank. You're finished.
掰掰
Ciao.
击沉他们 从他们的尸体上
Sink them and we can recover the Arrowhead
拿回箭镞!
from the bottom of the river!
装载鱼雷
Load torpedoes.
装载鱼雷!   -装载完成
Load torpedoes! MAN 2: Torpedo in. Closing the hatch!
谢谢   -喔 客气了
Thank you.  -Oh, you're welcome.
近一点 近一点
Closer. Closer.
莉莉  知道
Lily? Do you know,
法兰克 如果我是你...   -可惜你不是
if I were you, Frank... -Well, you're not me.
有时候只要这样
I just feel that sometimes it just needs a bit of a...
除了我，没人可以碰我的引擎
This is my engine. Nobody touches my engine but me.
我才刚说...
What did I just...
不客气
There you go.
掰掰啰
Goodbye.
那是...
Is that a...
鱼雷  -喔 我的妈呀
Torpedo. -Oh, my God.
法兰克 法兰克 法兰克
Frank, Frank, Frank!
法兰克 法兰克 法兰克 法兰克!
Frank, Frank, Frank, Frank!
你要干嘛?  -我们跑不赢
What are you doing?   -We can't outrun it.
法兰克!
Frank!
噢不
Oh.
看看他们对你做了什么 我的小宝贝
Look what they did to you. Poor thing.
机关枪的事我很抱歉
I'm so sorry. Machine guns.
但谁会把潜水艇开进这里呢
Who brings a submarine to the Amazon?
但我们又逃脱了 都靠你
But you still outran them. Every time.
我决定穿休闲一点
I thought I'd keep it casual.
你又再次超越了自己
Well, you've really outdone yourself this time.
那艘潜水艇有什么底细?
Do we know the identity of our homicidal maniac in the submarine?
我不知道名字
No, I don't know his name.
但德国皇帝的小儿子
But the youngest son of Kaiser Wilhelm
写了一篇关于月亮之泪的文章
wrote several articles about the Tears of the Moon.
我猜就是他
And if I had to guess, I would say that that's him.
它不热吗
Aren't you hot in all that?
一点也不
Not in the slightest.
我的眼睛在流汗
My eyeballs are sweating.
你还好吗，亲爱的
Are you all right, love?
喔 喔喔 我的天!  麦桂格 快看!
Oh, my... Oh, my goodness! MacGregor, look!
亚马逊河海豚!
Inia geoffrensis!
其实我们叫它 迷妖
You know, here we call them "encantado."
令人着魔的意思?  -对 会变身的精灵
"Bewitched"?  -Yeah. Shape-shifter spirits.
千万别直视它们的眼睛，除非你这辈子不想再好好睡觉
Don't look them directly in the eye unless you want nightmares for life.
你也相信诅咒，不是吗
You believe in legends, you should believe in curses, too.
好喔
Okay.
麦桂格
Hey, MacGregor.
我曾经有一个情人，斗鸡眼严重，后来分了
Had a girlfriend once, she was cross-eyed. Didn't work out.
根本没法集中注意力
We could never see eye to eye.
这是个笑话吗?
Oh, my God. Is that your idea of a joke?
一点也不好笑
That is not funny.
她很可能根本就看不到我的侧脸
I'm also quite sure she was seeing somebody on the side.
愚蠢
Silly.
法兰克 大部分的人看到镜头都会笑
You know, most people smile when they're on camera, Frank.
这是台让照片动的摄影机
It's a moving picture camera.
可以拍电影，见过吗
Have you never seen one before?
我没看过照片会动
I've never seen a moving picture.
很有趣的
They're so much fun
仿佛你能走遍了整个世界
and you can experience being anywhere in the world.
恩
Ah.
但当你身在此林中
Although, why would you want to,
何需如此?
if you could be here, surrounded by all this?
这里就
It's just...
好像漂浮在伊甸园里
Oh, it's like drifting through the Garden of Eden.
美不胜收
It's just beautiful.
金鸟赫蕉 看过吗?
Look at this. Frank, did you see these heliconias?
你知道在亚马逊的
Do you know there's more individual species
一棵树上的生物多样性都比...
on one tree in the Amazon than there is...
麦桂格，你走错方向了
MacGregor, I think you seem to be taking us off course.
应该要往那边航行
We should turn that way.
不，这方向才对
No, we're good. Stay on course.
哭泣水晶在那个方向
Lagrimas de Cristal is that way.
-法兰克 法兰克…  -他没错
Frank, Frank...  -He's fine.
你搞错了   -我没搞错 我才是船长
I'm not mistaken, I'm the skipper.
直直往前走就对了
The Lagrimas de Cristal is straight ahead.
维持方向
Stay on course.
法兰克 地图上标示这里可以通行
Frank, it says on the map that it's passable.
就那条岔路
Here we have that cliff
and exactly that tributary.
能省下两天
We can save two days going this way.
不能往那，必须往这
We cannot go that way. We have to go that way.
哭泣水晶就往那方向阿
Lagrimas de Cristal is that way.
开往那儿就是激流 你是没体验过吧？
We go that way, it's rapids. You ever been down the rapids?
没有 但我知道你有
No, but I presume that you have...
所以我才雇用你
Yes. -...which is why I hired you!
就
So just...
转弯 右转 急打右舷 随便你怎么说
turn that way. To the right. Starboard. Whatever you call it.
不会游泳的可不是我 长裤小姐
I'm not the one who can't swim, Pants.
不用你多管闲事 喘长
Don't you worry about that, Skippy.
船长
Lady, it's "Skipper."
我的错
My mistake.
这该死的雨林
This godforsaken, endless Amazon,
支流太多了吧
with its infinite tangled tributaries.
霍顿博士可能带着圣镞跑往任何一个方向
Dr. Houghton and the Arrowhead could be anywhere.
只有一个人
There's only one person
曾经与月亮之泪仅一步之遥
who has ever gotten close to the Tears of the Moon.
我们去找他谈谈吧，设定新航线
We shall have to ask him directly. We'll set a new course.
但阁下，阿吉雷的诅咒…
But, Your Highness, the curse of Don Aguirre...
只是个传说吧?
That's only a legend, right?
我们在这里下锚过夜
We're gonna anchor here for the night.
晚上不是问题吧，我们继续前进啊
Can't we make good time in the dark? Look, we can just keep going.
不要 除非你想要引擎过热
No, not unless you want
the engine to overheat.
好吧喘长 今天好累
Tell you what, Skippy. After this day,
我想要洗个舒服的澡
I could really do with that luxurious bath of yours.
浴室在下面吗?
Is it, um, down there?
长裤小姐，下面没浴室   -啥?
-No, there's no bath down there, Pants.  -What?
下面没浴室 浴室在那边
No, the bath is out there. That's the bath.
4300哩的超大奢华澡堂
4,300 miles of luxurious bath.
刚用太阳帮你加热的刚好
I also warmed it a little bit for you earlier.
对了 我知道你不会游泳 要是不小心溺水
Oh, and I know you don't know how to swim,
so if you happen to drown out there,
拿个肥皂，呃，用肥皂把自己洗上岸
go ahead and, uh, use the soap to wash yourself ashore.
我饿了
I could do with something to eat.
有人我的食物全丢在码头上了
Someone threw all of my reserve food
into the harbor.
法兰克 你以为饿死我们就能提早回程?
You know, Frank, if you think you're going to cut our trip short by starving us,
我告诉你这绝对  非常有可能
let me tell you that   that is extremely likely to work.
我还不如去吃...
Do you expect me to eat that?
噢
Oh...
食人鱼
Piranha.
你应该在它们吃你之前把它们吃掉
Better eat them before they eat you.
不可能
No way.
我得说 法兰克 出乎意料地好吃
Have to say, Frank. These piranha are so good.
但那是什么味道
Can't quite place that flavor, though.
血的味道
It's blood.
噢
Oh.
好
Right.
我先睡了
I'm to bed.
下面随便你躺，但千万别进我房间，那是禁区
Sleep anywhere you want downstairs, just not in my cabin. It's off-limits.
脑子坏掉才会进你房间
Why on Earth would I want to do that?
真衰
Bugger!
不要再盯着我了
You're staring, how do I make it stop?
就是穿长裤的女人真的很怪
I'm just not used to seeing a woman in pants, that's all.
你对我的穿着真的很有意见，法兰克
Awfully interested in my apparel, Frank.
习惯它吧
Get your head around it.
那双眼画的真是栩栩如生
You know, you really bring those eyes to life.
不过位置有点...偏
Your perspective's a little off, though.
哪有?
What?
好吧，你对，你意见真多
Well, you're right, annoyingly.
你会画画吗?   -以前会
Do you draw?  -I used to.
现在不画了?
Why'd you stop?
我已经画够了
Well, I drew everything I wanted to draw.
不知道要画什么了
Then I figured I'd learn something new.
也许你只是需要刺激
Or perhaps you just need some proper inspiration.
你呢?
What about you?
从来不缺刺激
Never lack for inspiration.
不，我意思是，你的目的到底是什么?
No, I mean, what're you doing out here?
你就喜欢在全世界追着地图跑? 这就你的娱乐?
Chasing maps all over the place? Or is this your idea of fun?
月亮之泪    -喔 别再...
The Tears of the Moon... -Oh, come on.
我相信传说是真的
I believe that the legend is real.
可惜不是   -我会找到它
Which it's not. -And I'm gonna find it.
可惜你找不到    -当我发现时
Which you won't.  -And when I do,
想像有多少生命能因此获救
just imagine the lives that could be saved.
传说有棵治愈神树能治愈一切
Legend says one petal from the Tree will heal anything.
这将永远改变现代医学知识
It will change medicine forever.
掀起一次巨大的科学革命
It's the beginning of a scientific revolution.
多么动人心弦 法兰克
It's very exciting, Frank.
你想成为花卉界的达尔文?
So, you wanna be the Darwin of flowers?
我想帮助人类
And I want to help as many people as I can.
你是救世主?
Wanna save the world?
我没这么说
I didn't say "save the world."
很高尚
It's very noble.
谢谢赞美    -又愚蠢
Well, thank you. -It's also very stupid.
"你真惹人厌"
"You are deeply unpleasant."
走音了啦
And off-key.
你宁愿冒着自己和弟弟的生命危险
So, you'd rather risk your life and your brother's life
去救你甚至都不认识的人?
to save people you don't even know?
我不需要认识任何人
Well, I don't have to know someone to care.
我没有一个可以在乎的人
Well, I don't have to care about anybody, period.
显而易见
That's apparent.
听着 人一辈子最重要
Look, I just think if you're lucky enough
就是至少有一个在乎的人
to have one person in this life to care about,
我的世界有他足矣
then that's world enough for me.
"我的世界有他足矣"
"That's world enough for me."
恩
Hmm.
喔 我的天  喔 我的妈呀
Oh, my goodness! Oh, my goodness! Oh, my...
麦桂格?
MacGregor!
普西玛  普西玛
Proxima! Proxima!
坐好 普西玛 坐好
Heel there, Proxima! Proxima, heel.
冷静
Heel.
普西玛
Proxima.
这是你的宠物?
This is your cat?
所以之前是在?
So, that fight?
演戏   -夭寿 法兰克
Faked it.  -For goodness' sake, Frank!
你到底有哪件事能让人信任
Is there a single thing about you that I can trust?
一根毛都没法
Not a thing.
时机选的真好啊
Great timing.
当地人对这个地方充满恐惧
The natives speak of this place with dread.
正是阿吉雷和他的部队试图拿走圣镞
This is where Aguirre and his men were punished
永生永世受到诅咒的地方
for trying to steal the Arrowhead.
那里
There.
河水
River water.
等很久了吧
This is what you have been waiting for.
看看这是谁啊
Look who is here.
传说活生生地出现在眼前呢
The legend in the flesh.
怀念河流吗?
River water. You want to see more?
苦苦等待着重回河边的机会
A long, painful wait to see the river again.
月亮之泪可以打破你的诅咒
The Tears of the Moon can break your curse,
放你自由
free you from this jungle.
你我都想获得月亮之泪
You want what I need.
雷管
Detonator.
圣镞离我们不远了
The Arrowhead is near.
帮我找到
You will find it for me,
我们各取其利 怎么样?
and we both get what we want. Deal?
你发誓
Swear it.
很好
Good.
我们快到搅拌机区域了 准备好了吗 长裤女士
All right, we're about to hit the butter churn. Ready, Pants?
你确定只有这条路吗
You sure this is the only way?
这可是你选的 你想抄捷径
You picked the route. You wanted to save two days.
那个 搅拌机是比喻吗?
Uh, "butter churn," how literal a metaphor?
如果你有贵重物品
If you have anything of value,
建议放在甲板下
I would recommend that you store it below deck.
我挺贵重的，那就...待会儿见啰
Since I consider myself of value, I will see you all on the other side.
等等，等等，等等
Wait a minute. MacGregor. Wait. Wait, wait, wait.
保护好它
Do not lose it.
看到了吗
You see that?
帮我弄过来
I want you to bring that to me.
认识你真是太好了
It's been lovely knowing you.
别讲这种话
Don't say that.
去吧
Go.
噢，又是你，走开
Oh, not you again. Go away.
你真确定吗 长裤女士
You sure you're up for this, Pants?
开你的船 喘长
Just drive the boat, Skippy.
这猫好粗鲁啊
That ruddy cat!
你在干嘛   -她不乖
What are you doing? -She's incessant.
来了
Here we go.
喔我的天
Oh, my God!
还好吗 女士
You okay, lady?
我很好   -后悔了吗 长裤
I'm fine.  -You wanna turn back, Pants?
好戏才正要开始
Nope. Just getting started.
加一
Good. Me, too.
慢点!
Slow down!
后悔了吗?
You wanna turn back?
开你的船!
Just drive!
你尿裤子了 长裤女士
Looks like you wet your pants, Pants.
是被水溅到的
That was the wave.
放弃吧
You should give up.
你这音痴才该放弃你的吉他
You should give up the guitar.
天啊
Oh, my God!
来吧，伙计
Come on, buena nina.
撑住
Come on!
千万别再来一次
Please don't ever do that again.
那咱们掉头去逛小镇 怎么样?
I could turn the boat around and we could head back to town, how's that?
不知道原来你这么明智
That may be the first intelligent thing you've said since we met.
长裤小姐意下如何?
How about you, Pants?
逛小镇?
You ready to go back to town?
不要?
No?
我其实很享受 呃 这个过程
I actually loved, uh, the whole experience.
发现 呃 很来劲
I... I found it, um, exhilarating.
你脸色都发青了
You're looking a little green around the gills.
别硬撑了 你还行不?
That's why I'm asking.  Are you okay?
饿吗
Are you hungry?
对 她饿了
Yeah, she's hungry.
来条烟薰食人鱼
Have some cured piranha if you think you...
你拿到了吗
Did you get it?
啊哈
Ugh!
你醉了?
You're drunk?
从没见过这么弱的猫
You're the worst cat I have ever had.
真不明白你怎么能忍受那女人
I don't know how you live with that woman.
才认识两天，我就想把她扔进河里了
I've been with her for two days, and I already wanna throw her overboard.
需要一些时间适应
Does take some getting used to.
她有没有没那么...过?
Does she ever stop being so, uh...
莉莉?    -对
Lily?  -Yes.
恐怕是不可能
Afraid not.
一头栽进去就死不撒手
Headfirst, figure it out on the way down.
应该刻在她的拉丁文徽章上
It should be on her crest in Latin.
不错
Hmm.
在干嘛呢
What you doing?
挖自己的坟墓吧
Your funeral.
偷瞄一下不行吗
It's just a peek.
你姐想说什么就说什么
Your sister says whatever she wants to say
想对谁说就对谁说
to whoever she wants to say it.
都不管人家心里会不会受伤
No regard for anybody's feelings.
受伤的往往都是我
Doesn't matter who gets hurt. Usually me.
她跟父亲很像
She takes after our father.
总是追寻一些不切实际的想法
He was always chasing after some far-fetched idea.
这世界上才没有什么诅咒 或治愈神树
There's no such thing as curses. Or cure-alls.
这里已经三个世纪没有征服者经过了
And there hasn't been a conquistador here for three centuries.
恩
Hmm.
那你为何要跟着她东奔西走
So, why'd you follow her out here, then?
当我第三次
It was the third time that I'd been presented
在马厩前被求婚的时候
with an entirely suitable marriage
她是一个迷人、聪明又完美的女人
to a charming, educated woman that sits on a horse well,
但是我当下拒绝了她
that I had to tell the lady in question
我没有选择，只能说
that I couldn't accept the offer.
我不能娶她 不能娶任何人
Or, indeed, any offer,
因为我对她不感兴趣 我对
given that my interests happily lie...
别的地方感兴趣
elsewhere.
别的地方?
Elsewhere?
别的地方
Elsewhere.
喔
Huh.
敬 那个地方
Well... To elsewhere.
叔叔威胁要剥夺我的继承权
Uncle threatened to disinherit me,
家人和朋友全都背我而去
friends and family turned their backs...
就因为我喜欢的对象
all because of who I loved.
整个社会抛弃我
I would've been ostracized from society
但莉莉没有
were it not for Lily.
她始终支持我
She stood by me.
就这点 我愿意跟随她上刀山下火海
And for that, I would follow her into a volcano.
裤子!  该走了!
Pants! Let's shove off!
你要不要解释一下?
Would you care to explain this?
说过离我房间远点
I said stay out of my quarters.
我想也是
Oh, I bet you did.
这样你的秘密才不会被我们发现
So that you could keep more secrets from us.
剥开谎言还是谎言 法兰克 你就像一颗洋葱
Just lie upon lie. I mean, Frank, you are like an onion of deceit.
什么谎言?    -你曾经找过月亮之泪
What lies?   -That you're after it yourself!
我不找了，不再找了
I am not after it! Not anymore.
很久很久以前的事了
Not for a long, long time.
好吧 没错
Okay, yes,
我曾来寻找月亮之泪，跟你一样
I came here seeking the Tears of the Moon, just like you.
长这样的地图
I have a map just like yours.
好几打长得很像的地图
And a dozen others just like it.
阿吉雷的制图师显然灵感泉源不绝
Aguirre's cartographer certainly was prolific.
可惜他死后一无所获
Yeah, well, he lost his life searching for something that can't be found.
我调查了每个村庄，每个岛屿，每个港口
I've tracked the legend to every village, every island, every shoal.
啥都没有
Nothing.
从此我身陷泥潦
And now I'm stuck on this river ever since,
真希望我从来没来过这条河
wishing I could be anywhere else but here.
但是你没有这个
But you never had this.
我要摸你 别咬我
I'm going to pet you now. And you're not going to eat me.
懂吗
Understood?
慢慢来
Easing in.
准备接触
About to engage.
对一只毛茸茸的杀人大猫来说 你其实也不坏
You're not that bad really, are you, for a big, hairy murder cat?
我通常不会那么冒犯
I don't usually offend so immediately.
莉莉!
Lily!
麦桂格
MacGregor.
噢
Oh...
我们到底要去哪里
Where are they taking us?
正朝向猎头村
We're headed into headhunter territory,
带着头过去会被"猎头"
which is a terrible place to be headed.
喔 法兰克 时机很差耶
Oh, Frank, come on, not now.
忍不住
I can't turn it off.
莉莉!
Lily!
法兰克!
Frank!
法兰克
Frank.
麦桂格
...MacGregor...
你刚说啥?
What did you say?
我告诉他们得放了你们兄妹俩活着离开
I said that they should let you and your brother MacGregor go, and live.
并留下所有家当衣服作为交换
In exchange, you'll have to leave all of your things and your clothes,
我自个儿留下当人质
and I'll stay back as well.
你好勇敢
That's very, very brave.
但我不同意，法兰克，我们不可能丢下你
That is not something I agree to, Frank. We're not doing it.
三个人活着离开是不可能的
There's no way that the three of us can get out of this situation alive.
我知道这种部落，现在走还有机会...
I know these people. Leave now and let them...
不!   -可以给我五分钟
No! -Can I please talk for five minutes
好好听我说话嘛!
-without you interrupting me?
噢 你有五分钟了
Oh, now you've done it.
噢不
Oh, no.
"我唯一想要的"
"The only thing of yours I want
"是那个箭头"  - 不可以
"is the Arrowhead."   - No.
千万别摇头，他们不喜欢的
Don't shake your head like that. They hate that.
他们不喜欢摇头
They hate that. Don't do that.
"我知道你有"
"I know you have it.
"本该属于我们族人的物品"
"It belongs to my people, taken long ago.
"还回来 你就能离开"
"You can return it and go free.
"或者让我将它连你手指一起砍下"
"Or I can pry it from your fingers.
"再把它从碎肉里取出来"
"After I pick them clean of meat."
噢
Oh.
快点，善良的食人族在鼓励你
Come on. You heard the nice cannibal.
还给他们   -我不太擅长
Hand it over.  -I'm a little rusty
普卡米那丘话
in the Puka Michuna dialect,
你必须一字不差的翻译
so I want you to translate what I say, word for word.
没问题
Okay.
不，我不会给你箭镞
No, I cannot give you the Arrowhead.
噢 天啊莉莉    -莉莉
Oh, God. Lily.  -Lily.
闭嘴，给我翻译
Shut up. Just say it.
没错，我是有你们族人的箭镞
Yes, I have the Arrow that belongs to your people.
她对箭镞很着迷
She's being weird about the Arrowhead.
我会还你们的
I will return it.
她很难搞
She's extremely difficult.
但我得先找到月亮之泪
But first I must use it to find the Tears of the Moon.
她真的很顽固
It's hard to be around her.
我甘愿因此而死
Now, if I die for that, so be it.
她不在乎你们会不会杀了她
She doesn't mind if you kill her.
但你得放了我旁边两人离开
But you must let these two men go free.
但她求你保我一命
Just don't kill me.
莉莉!
Lily!
来啊 跟我打架 你 跟我打架啊
Come on, fight me. You, come on, fight me.
快啊 你有什么毛病
Go! Do it! What's wrong with you?
莉莉...
Lily...
法兰克 认真的
Seriously, Frank.
你要这不嘎不嘎的套路，下次要付更多钱
Next time I'm going to charge you more for this "booga-booga" nonsense.
山姆 我们说好的 好吗
Sam, we had a deal, okay?
不 不 我已经厌倦了你这愚蠢的服装
No, no. I'm tired, and this is a whole production,
和你的耍猴烂戏
with these ridiculous costumes!
你明明就说
And you told me
会是一个天真的女孩和一个懦弱的哥哥
this was a nice English lady with her wimpy brother.
结果她宁愿自杀?
And she's gonna get herself killed.
我知道 她根本是疯...子
I know, because she's crazy!
疯狂的顽固份子
She's crazy determined.
莉莉，我坦白，我没机会取消这个桥段
Lily, listen, the truth is I didn't get a chance to call this entire thing off.
如果你信以为真，很抱歉这只是个骗局
Remember, it's only a scam if you fall for it.
别再这样做了
You've gotta stop doing that.
懦弱 哈?   -强而有力的懦弱
Wimpy, eh?   -In a strong way.
拳头真硬  你全家都有够硬
Strong form. The whole family has strong form.
你能破译它吗?
Can you translate it?
有机会
Possibly.
可能，但是你知道，有点障碍
Possibly, but, you know, there are some impediments.
你有所求的时候英语说得可真标准
Your English gets very exact when you want something.
有一种要谈价格的预感
I have the tingling impression we're to negotiate a price.
你懂我
You get me.
"商人山姆 "喜欢做交易
Trader Sam likes a trade.
果不其然
Oh, I bet.
喜欢帽子吗?  -恩...
Would you like that hat? -Hmm.
它是你的了
You can have that hat.
你做的真成功
You've really done it now.
她会原谅我吗?   -想得美
You think she'll get over it?  -Not likely.
我不是针对你们 这计划已经安排很久了
It wasn't personal, you know. It was a pre-existing arrangement.
敢这样背叛莉莉，你已经死透千百万次
Cross Lily like that and you are dead to her.
烧成灰烬
Dead and buried.
尸骨无存
Entombed.
烧成灰烬尸骨无存   -好好 我明白了
Embalmed and entombed. -I got it.
像渡渡鸟一样从地球上消失   -好了 够清楚了
Dead as a dodo.   -You're making it very clear.
死掉 灭绝 消失   -麦先生
Dead, dead, dead.  -MacGregor.
这啤酒还不错耶
This beer's actually rather nice.
是唾酵而成的   -恩哼
It's masato.  -Hmm.
口水发酵而成的
It's made out of fermented spit.
你在喝别人的口水
You're drinking spit.
有一次我在罗马...
When in Rome.
天啊 真希望我在罗马
God, I wish I was in Rome.
"月亮之泪"
"The Tears of the Moon
"拥有治愈一切的力量"
"possess the power to cure anything."
看看这个字
Now, this word here,
英语中没有对应的文字 意思是...
there's no exact translation in English. It's...
一种对灵魂的
a pain to...
折磨...
the soul.
治疗 治疗
Heal. Heal.
一种对灵魂的治疗
Heal the soul.
差不多
Pretty much.
恩恩 治疗
Mm-hmm. Heal.
"要证明你的价值，必须化水为石"
"To prove yourself worthy, you must turn water to stone.
"并修补一颗破碎的心"
"Then mend a broken heart."
噢
Ooh.
"让泪水绽放..."
"For Tears to bloom,
"让大树在月下哭泣"
"the great Tree must be under the rare crying Moon."
两天后就是新月了
There is one in two days.
"月亮流血之处"
"The Tree hides
"将是树木藏身之处"
"where the Moon bled.
"月将从西边落下，割过蛇的心脏"
"It sank into the west, over the heart of the serpent."
蛇
Serpent.
"在毒牙咬尾之处"
"Where the fang bites its own tail..."
"在毒牙咬尾之处"  喔 我的天
"Where the fang bites its tail." Oh, my goodness.
就说这很复杂了吧
Now, I told you it was complicated.
难怪没人找的到
Of course no one's ever found it.
没错，根本就不在哭泣水晶
Right, because it's not in Lagrimas de Cristal.
是这里  碎月之地
It's here. La Luna Rota.
没错
Yes.
你觉得多久能到
How long would you say it would take me to get down there?
两天或三天吧
Two or three days.
搭独木舟呢
What about via canoe?
你说什么?
Excuse me?
跟喘船长说我从现在开始一个人走
Please inform Captain Skippy that I will be traveling alone from now on.
你不会一个人 莉莉
You're never gonna make it alone, Lily.
告诉他低估了我的决心 还有我的操船技术
Please tell him that he misjudges my determination, also my driving skills.
那么请告诉裤子博士 雨林有多危险
Please tell Dr. Pants that what's out there in the jungle,
告诉她 这可不是在读小说
she's never read about in her little textbooks. Tell her that.
哈 我不会再被你可笑的把戏玩弄的
Well, I'm not gonna be falling for any more of his ludicrous tricks.
你的玩笑越来越鸡肋了
They're getting really tedious.
如果你戴着那玩意儿独自往上游
If you go upriver by yourself with that thing around your neck,
没办法活着回来   -这样啊
you're never gonna make it out alive.  -Really?
我们得团结一心
We have to stick together.
我们?  -对 我们
Do we? -Yes, we do.
"我们"是个挺耐人寻味的词 法兰克
"We" is an interesting word, Frank.
没有诚实和信任，似乎行不通喔
Because it sort of implies a bond of trust and honesty.
不过你也不懂 因为你就是个骗子 法兰克
Neither of which you know anything about, because you are a liar, Frank.
自私又自大
You are selfish, you are arrogant,
我打死不会再相信你，能扔你多远有多远
and I wouldn't trust you as far as I could throw you,
大概也不远 因为你满大的
which clearly isn't very far, because you are huge.
所以 再也没有"我们"
So, there is no more "we," actually.
剩下的12,000就此结清
In fact, here's the rest of your 12,000.
噢 这些小费用来感谢你丰富的安排
Oh, and here's a tip for such wonderful service.
这是把球杆
This one is a driver.
"球杆"
TRIBESPEOPLE: Driver.
没错，任何你想要打去远方的东西 就靠他
Yes. Use that for anything over 200 yards.
你还需要 铁杆
Under that, you'll need an iron.
战妆  真酷
War paint? Righto, yes.
我是战士 来吧
For a warrior. Dilly!
有点痒
Tickles.
感觉不会脱落
This doesn't appear to be coming off.
这是纹身染料，会脱落的
That's 'cause it's tattoo ink. It'll come off eventually.
几十年后吧
In a few decades.
喔 惨了
Oh, no.
法兰西斯科...
Francisco...
莉莉!    -噢 法兰克 干嘛
Lily!  -Oh... Frank, what?
我们得马上离开  -什么?
We have to get out of here now. -What?
-给我圣镞   -当我白痴吗?
-Give me the Arrowhead. -Do you think I'm a fool?
你一定觉得我很好唬弄
I think you must think I'm a fool.
法兰西斯科...
Francisco...
发生什么事?  -我正要告诉你
What's going on?   -That's what I was trying to tell you.
不
No.
你好像很惊讶
You seem surprised.
传说应验了
It's impossible.
神话是真的
The myth is real.
辗转了四百年
After 400 years...
圣镞
The Arrowhead...
该还给我了
...belongs to me.
快去救大家   -好!
Save your family!  -Yes!
喔 天啊
Oh, God!
法兰克 法兰克 法兰克!
Frank, Frank! Frank!
快点 我抓住你 裤姐 相信我
Come on. I got you, Pants. Trust me.
抓紧了!
Hold on!
法兰克? 法兰克  勾住
Frank? Frank, get it.
快好了   -加把劲
Hold on. -Come on.
法兰克 加把劲  -我勾得住
Frank, please.  -I got it.
法兰克   -我勾不住
Frank.  -I don't got it.
法兰克!!  -妈妈咪啊!
Frank!  -Oh, my God!
放我下来啦 在干嘛啦!   -我在设法利用地心引力
Frank, get off me! What're you doing? -I'm trying to get traction.
这太荒唐了，让我走！  -不 一下下就好
This is ridiculous! -No, no, wait.
放我下来啦!  根本灾难...
Just leave me alone! That was a disaster!
你太重了
You're too heavy.
麦桂格!
MacGregor!
莉莉?
Lily?
抱歉
Sorry.
放开她
Get off her!
不!   -阿吉雷!
No! -Aguirre!
球杆
Driver.
老兄 射的真准  -圣镞
Lovely shot, sir.  -The Arrow.
不!
No!
法兰克!
Frank!
我们该走了 快来
We gotta go! Come on!
进去 拿那把刀!
Get in! Grab that knife!
就是现在!
Now!
你怎么了? 你做了什么?
Are you all right? What have you done?
没事 没事
It's all right. It's all right.
快走 离开这片河域 再也不要回头
You must go. Get out of sight of the river and run.
阿吉雷只想要圣镞
Aguirre only wants the Arrowhead.
尽全力跑  -快
Just run as fast as you can. -Go.
他们追来了! 快! 远离这片河域
They're coming! Go! Get away from the river!
我抓到她了
I have her!
不
No!
给我圣镞!
Give me the Arrowhead!
阿吉雷 我们离河流太远了!
Aguirre, we're too far from the river!
喔 我的天
Oh, my God!
没事 没事，是我，是我
It's cool. It's me. It's me.
有看到圣镞吗?
Did you see the Arrowhead?
有看到没?
Have you really seen it?
我不只看到，还拿手上呢
Not only have I seen it, I held it in my hands.
终于能解开诅咒了
Finally we can break the curse...
法兰西斯科该偿命了
and Francisco shall pay.
别管法兰西斯科了，阿吉雷，我们要圣镞
Forget about Francisco! The Arrowhead, Aguirre!
找到月亮之泪才能解开我们的诅咒
Only the Tears of the Moon can help us get out of this curse.
这片丛林快把我们吃光抹净了
This jungle is devouring our souls.
现在这样真恶心
We are disgusting.
那是你 我香的很
Speak for yourself. I am delicious.
你觉得我们的灵魂还在吗
Do you really believe we still have souls?
所以才需要月亮之泪 那是唯一的希望
That's why we need the Tears of the Moon, they are our only hope.
那个穿长裤的女人拿走圣镞了
The woman in pants has the Arrowhead...
远离了河边
and has taken it away from the river.
她知道我们没办法离开太远
Because she knows we can't follow her there.
王子
The Prince.
王子可以
He can follow the Arrowhead.
叫他去追
Tell him where she went.
你听到了
You heard him.
去通知王子
Tell the Prince.
麦桂格!
MacGregor!
法兰克?
Frank?
法兰克 你还活着
Frank, you're alive.
你还活着，但怎么会呢
How? How are you alive, Frank?
我亲眼看到你死掉
I saw you die.
你摔落下去了 怎么还活着
I saw you fall. How are you alive?
莉莉，不管你曾经为我做了什么
Lily, I don't care what you've done for me,
如果我们能活着离开这里...   -噢 你在这
if we make it out of here alive... -Oh, there you are.
我再也不会离开肯辛顿
...I am never leaving Kensington again.
对 他还活者
Yeah. Frank's alive.
哦 恩 那个
Huh. Oh, um...
你背后有东西
You've got a little, um, something in your back.
法兰克?
Frank?
法兰西斯科才对
The name's actually Francisco.
法兰西斯科-洛佩斯-德-埃雷迪亚
Francisco Lopez de Heredia.
而且
And...
我大概有400岁了
I'm roughly 400 years old.
什么鬼?  -我知道一时很难接受
What?  -I know it's a lot to take in.
待我娓娓道来   -你没流血
I will explain to you the entire story...  -There's no blood in you.
你是鬼吗?
Are you a ghost?
不 有点复杂
No, it's complicated.
但 你 你很明显不是人类
But clearly you're... you're not a human.
好 好吧 但刀子插在我心脏上 我有点难专心
Okay, but it's very hard to focus when I have a sword impaled in my heart.
山姆 帮我一把
Trader Sam, I need you to come and pull.
吸血鬼?
Vampire?
我说过了 我不想再从你身上拔出任何东西
I told you last time, I'm done pulling weapons out of you.
噢 不
Oh, no.
你是 是博士 对吧
It is, uh, Dr. Houghton, right?
植物学
Of Botany.
哇 它完全刺穿了
Look at it. It's just hanging out like that.
剑就是这么用的
Well, it's how it's made.
刀片的形状很奇怪
It's got a very strange shape.
看到了吗？就 那样...
Have you seen it out the back? It's like... Woo... Like that.
不，它 它就是直直的刺穿了
Well, it's not... It's kinda actually just straight.
我要一只手吗 还是两手一起
One hand, two hand, what do you want?
先试试一只
Let's try one.
看来你需要两只
You're gonna need two hands.
不 不 不!
No, no, no!
怎么 怎么...?   -喔天啊 痛死了
What, what, what? -Oh, my gosh! That hurts.
才怪    -你又知道?
No, it doesn't. -How do you know?
法兰克 想要咬我的棒子吗?
Frank, would you like to bite down on my stick?
不 我不是..我不要 谢谢!  -我意思是...
Nope. I'm good. Thank you.  -No, for the pain.
我知道你的意思
I understand what it...
他的意思... 但是，不要
What he means. But no.
永远为你准备好
There if you need it.
我觉得你太紧绷了
I just feel like you're very uptight right now.
这样无济于事 我已经够紧张了
And it's not helping me 'cause I'm very nervous.
没关系 人总有第一次
It's okay to be nervous. It's your first time.
第一次对吧?
It is your first time, right?
废话 法兰克   -我懂 我懂 看的出来
Yes, you know it is, Frank. -I know, I know. I can tell.
我拔过上百次了
I've done this hundreds of times.
我不知道怎么出力 法兰克    -这把很特别
I don't know how to take that, Frank. -This is special.
有吗   -很特别
Is it? -It is.
慢点!   -干嘛?
Slow! -What?
这样行不通的
Oh, you can't do it like that.
好难   -法兰克
That's way too hard. -Frank.
需要我帮忙边拔边转吗
Would you like me to give it a wiggle?
这个好   -不可以!
Yes. Yes. -Absolutely not.
我从后面推 一次解决怎么样
I could pop around the back and give it a once over.
不 这样够了   -好吧
No, we're good. -Okay.
这可能有用 脚蹬着他
You know what always helps? If you put your foot on it.
我有点紧张 -不用紧张
I'm a little nervous.  -Don't be nervous.
法兰克，我数到三
Frank, I'm gonna count to three.
你会直接...还是我来数
You're gonna... I'm counting or...
我数
No, I'm counting.
一       -啊啊啊!
One.  -'Cause... Ahhh!
我梦见我在一个俱乐部里吃饭
I dreamt I was lunching at Boodle's.
博士，来吧
Hey, Doctor.
该走了  -当然
We should go. -Of course.
不 你为我做够多了
No. You've done enough.
不能把你一个人丢在外面
I can't leave you alone out here.
你看看你 根本走不动
Look at the state of you. And you can't even walk.
你会回来吧?
Will you at least consider turning back?
我会没事的 保证
I will be fine. I promise.
我闻起来?
Do I smell?
遭透了
Horrendously.
有客人，打开舱门
We have visitors. Open the hatch.
午安 朋友们
Good afternoon, my friends.
那儿有东西吗?
Something is there?
找到啥了? 你找到他们的渡轮了吗
What is there? You have found their river boat?
没有?
No?
没有船，那圣镞呢?
Not the river boat? The Arrowhead?
圣镞? 对 在哪里
The Arrowhead? Yes. Show... Show me where.
一只蜜蜂在对我们发号施令耶
We're taking orders from a bee.
在地图上指一下
Show me on the map.
这?
Here?
对 你听到了没 改变航向!
Yes! You heard him. Change course!
可以请蜜蜂说一下坐标吗
Could you ask the bee for coordinates?
少得寸进尺 克赛尔
Don't be ridiculous, Axel.
谢谢
Thank you.
过了395年
395 years...
5个月又13天
...five months and 13 days.
真以为你死了
I really thought you died.
你有难过吗?
Were you sad when I died?
我很关心
I was very concerned.
我的灵魂
For my soul.
我的探险
For my expedition.
还有你
And for you.
你到底是什么
So, what are you?
不流血，但是会呼吸
You don't bleed, I think you breathe.
根本不可能
You're not possible.
我搞不清楚我现在是什么
I don't know what I am anymore.
但是我可以告诉你我曾经是什么
But I can tell you what I was.
我父亲是雇佣兵
My father was a mercenary
当时在阿尔及尔被阿吉雷父亲招募到麾下
and he was recruited by Aguirre's father in Algiers.
当我父亲代他而死时，他收留了我
When my father died protecting him, he took me in.
把我和阿吉雷当亲兄弟一样扶养
Raised Aguirre and me together, like brothers.
后来阿吉雷的女儿生了重病
Aguirre's daughter Anna had fallen ill.
阿吉雷只有一个孩子，所以不顾一切想救活她
She was all he had. He vowed he wouldn't lose her.
我需要离开一阵子
I will travel far.
但我会带着月亮之泪回来的
But I will come back to you with a Tear of the Moon.
你可以再次在月光下奔跑
And you will run again in the moonlight.
无病无痛地
Healed.
我们征服了大海 却栽在河流里
We fought the ocean, only to be beaten by the river.
雨林让我们举步维艰
The jungle fought our every step.
为了月亮之泪，我不惜一切
I would've done anything to find the Tears of the Moon
去拯救阿吉雷的女儿
and save Aguirre's daughter.
绘出整片亚马逊地型
Even chart the Amazon.
你是阿吉雷的制图师?
You were Aguirre's cartographer?
我的地图是你画的?
You drew my map?
法兰克...
Frank...
怎么样 我画得不错吧
Really think my work is extraordinary?
我同意 你是个小大师级的画家
I think you were a minor master of your time.
小大师?
Minor?
队员一个接着一个被雨林带走
One by one, the jungle took us.
但即使面对死亡，阿吉雷仍在坚持
We were all but dead. Still, Aguirre wouldn't turn back.
失去女儿 他就失去了活下去的意义
There was no world for him without his daughter in it.
然后他们来了
And then they came.
如果不是因为月亮之泪，我们早就已经死了
We would've all died had they not saved us with the Tears of the Moon.
花瓣的魔法是真的
The petal's magic was real.
酋长和酋长之女释放了治愈之力
Its powers unlocked by the Chief and his daughter.
花瓣所到之处
All that was broken, the petals mended.
一下就恢复，很快就被治愈了
And all at once, we were revived.
阿吉雷开心死了
And Aguirre was happy,
救活女儿的希望是如此接近
because he was closer than ever to finding a cure for his daughter.
但他开始变得没耐心
But he grew impatient.
他跟部落索要圣镞
Aguirre demanded they give him the Arrowhead
并带他去治愈之树底下
and take him to the Tree.
你不够格
You are not worthy.
酋长拒绝了
The Chief refused.
尽管族人慷慨施予我们新生
Despite all the kindness they'd shown us,
阿吉雷却痛下杀手 赶尽杀绝
he would've killed every last one of them.
圣镞在她那!
She has the Arrowhead!
阿吉雷是我手足，但是我没法接受屠杀
I loved Aguirre, but I couldn't be part of the madness.
我不会害你
I'm not going to hurt you.
我只想要圣镞
I only want the Arrowhead.
但我也没办法袖手旁观
And I couldn't just stand by.
交出来!
Give it to me!
跑!
Run!
不!
No!
兄弟之情伤人最深
A brother's blade cuts deepest.
你这个叛徒
Traitor.
酋长知道自己大去之期不远矣
The Chief knew he was breathing his last breath.
他用最后一口气来守护圣镞
And he used that breath to protect the Arrowhead
和他们的神树
and their sacred Tree.
降下诅咒到阿吉雷身上
He cursed Aguirre.
到我们所有人身上 永生永世不得离开河边
He cursed all of us, so that we could never leave sight of the river again.
她往哪跑了?   -跑不远的!
Where did she go? -She can't be far!
丛林会一次又一次把我们拖回去
Or the jungle would take us back to it, for all eternity.
阿吉雷恨我入骨
Aguirre hated me for betraying him.
经年累月追着我跑，我们打斗
He found me over the years, and we fought.
一次又一次
And fought again.
我不想再被捅刀了
I got tired of being stabbed.
所以把他们引入山洞陷阱
So I made sure he would never hurt me or anyone else again.
确保再也碰不到我
I trapped them in a cave.
河流!
The river!
在哪?
Where is it?
丛林没法再把他们拖回河边
Where the jungle couldn't take them back to the river.
快离开这里!
We have to get out of here!
法兰西斯科 你会偿命的!
Francisco, you will pay for this!
往后300年 丛林蹂躏他们的身体
And for 300 years, the jungle ravaged their bodies.
于是他们就变成了现在这副模样
Turning them into the monsters they are today.
不知道他们是怎么被释放的
I don't know how they got free,
总之我好长一段时间都安安稳稳的
but I was safe for a long time.
那你都在干嘛?
What did you do?
这个嘛 我打造了一个小镇
Well, I made the best of it. I built a town.
挺好玩的
And that was fun.
交了些朋友
Made some friends.
也失去了些朋友
Lost some friends.
让我下定决心寻找月亮之泪
That's when I decided to search for the Tears of the Moon.
我造了一艘船
I built a boat.
以月亮女神之名命名为 "奎娜号"
And I named her after the goddess of the moon, Quila.
乘着它去遍每条支流和角落
I charted every inch of this river, searching.
直到我彻底放弃
Till I finally gave up.
因为我根本没办法离开河边半步
And since I could never leave sight of the river,
所以我开办丛林航游 噱一些观光客
I started giving jungle cruises to tourists.
好孤独啊
All that time, all alone...
也不完全啦
Well, not entirely alone, of course.
没错
That's right.
我开始领养流浪动物
Over the years, I would find strays that needed someone.
死了一只再换一只 换了又死 死了又换
The next, after the next, after the next.
小普西玛 老普西玛 阿祖普西玛...
And la proxima, la proxima...
普西玛?    -普西玛，对
La proxima? Proxima, yes,
全都取名普西玛   -噢
I name 'em all Proxima. -Oh, la proxima.
喔 不过你是我最爱的普西玛
Oh, but don't worry, you're my favorite girl.
时间就飞呀飞呀飞
Merrily, merrily, merrily, merrily
人生如诗
Life is but a dream
你应该要接下去第二段的
You're meant to join in on the second verse.
我再来一次喔
I'll do it again, shall I?
划 划 划
Row, row, row...
求你了 闭嘴
I'm begging you, stop!
到底到了没?
Are we there yet?
还没!
No!
想到一个
Got one.
我的小眼找到了
I spy with my little eye
第一个字母是...
something beginning with...
"S."
要不要搭便船？
Thought you might want a lift.
嘿!
Hey!
我不喜欢和陌生人共乘一船
I don't take lifts from strangers.
茶?
Cup of tea?
那么，喜欢你的丛林吗?
So, how do you enjoy this jungle?
不好意思?
I beg your pardon?
这个丛林
This jungle.
你说什么?   -丛林
Yeah, sorry? -The jungle.
慢慢地
Try it slower.
丛林
The jungle.
放在一个句子中
Could you pop it in a sentence?
有树 有虫 有丛林
The trees, the bugs... The... The jungle.
丛林?    -对 讲很多次了
The jungle?  -Yes. That is what I said.
好吧    -喜欢丛林吗?
Right. -How do you enjoy it?
有点慢慢变喜欢
It's actually rather grown on me.
我他妈不在乎了
I don't care anymore.
长官，到达目的
Sir, we have arrived at the target.
阿，是时候来个交易了
Ah. Time to make a deal.
看那边
Look, right through here.
是不是有个和蔼的米丘纳小村
You see the peaceful Puka Michuna tribe?
我只要按下这个按钮
With the touch of this button here,
就能一次干掉400个人
I could end 400 innocent lives.
他们要怪就怪自己怎么还活着
Their only crime being that they are still living.
你也可以告诉我 你姐姐和圣镞在哪
Your sister and the Arrowhead were here. Now, I need to know where she is going.
选择权在你手上
The choice is yours.
要他们生 还是死
Do they live or do they die?
帮你吧   -不要，轮到我了
Let me help you. No, it's my turn.
好的 大人说的是
Okay. You gotta listen to her.
完美  -真不错
It's perfect. -Pretty good.
现在可以放它自己滑行了
Yeah. Now we can just cruise.
人们找了这东西好久了
Do you know how many years people have been looking for that?
这老东西?    -对，那老东西
This old thing?  -Yeah. That old thing.
你怎么拿到手的
How is it that you turn up with it?
偷的
Stole it.
你偷的?
You stole it?
解放了它 这样怎么样
Liberated it. How about that?
好..
Okay.
我已经找了很多年，现在是你的了
I've searched for this thing for so long, but I'm pretty sure it belongs to you.
找到神树的话你想做什么
What are you gonna do when you find the Tree?
解开诅咒
Lift the curse.
那你会发生什么事
And what will happen to you?
恩...
Well...
我得做出个选择
I get to make a choice.
选择安息
And I choose to rest.
嘿 莉莉 听我说
Hey, Lily, look.
这世界的一切对你来说都很新颖
Everything that you see that's new in this world,
对我来说却是老调常弹了
I've seen hundreds of thousands of times.
但没有一刻比现在更有意义
Yes, but none of it has been meaningful.
他们在哪?
All right. Where are they?
我认不太出...
I don't actually recognize the specific...
哪里?    -这
Where?  -There.
你应该有打到
I think you got it.
神树是我的囊中之物
The Tree is here and will be ours.
不能让蜜蜂的主人知道这个位置
I cannot share my discoveries with their masters.
你在下面多久了?
You've been down here a while?
这一定是那个"巨石之水"
This has got to be "water to stone."
爬上去怎么样?
Do you think that we climb?
我觉得不是往上
I don't think we're meant to go up.
运气不错
We're in luck.
下面石室里有一个拉杆
There's a chamber down there with a lever in it.
我觉得那是关键
I think pulling it is the key.
那很好啊!
That's wonderful!
超棒 完美
It's wonderful. It's fantastic.
有个问题是 我们的祖先
Only problem is that the ancients who built all of this
比较瘦一点
were on average narrower.
恩 恩    -所以换你上场啰
Mm-hmm. -So, it's a great time for you
终于能洗个好澡啰
to take the finest bath in all Brazil.
不不不 法兰克 拜托别  -要 裤子小姐 听着
No, no, no. Frank, Frank, please! -Yes. Pants, listen...
我不会游泳 我不会
I cannot swim, Frank. That is not something I can do.
你又没试过
You've never tried.
跟那无关 我打从心里怕水
It's not about trying. I have this very deep fear.
我负责游泳
I'll do all the swimming.
法兰克 拜托...   -听我说
Frank, please. -Listen... Look,
我不能没有你
I can't do this without you.
我需要你来完成
I need you.
相信我好吗
You have to trust me.
不，不要 法兰克 法兰克 法兰克 拜托
No, no. Frank, Frank, Frank, please.
我以为你...
I thought you might, uh...
转过去 眼睛盯着瀑布 老喘长
Just turn around and look at the waterfall, Skippy.
好不好?  -好好好
All right? Please. -Fine. Whew.
不准偷看
Don't look.
你是裤子里面还有穿裤子?
Are you wearing pants under your pants?
对  -天阿 法兰克!
Yes. -Oh, my God! Frank!
没事 没关系的
It's okay. It's okay.
准备好   -我还没...不 不!
Here we go. -I'm not... No, no!
等等! 有东西在碰我的脚 法兰克!
Wait a minute! Something just touched my foot, Frank!
没事，没事，那是我的脚趾头
It's okay, it's okay. It was my foot.
喔 我很抱歉
Oh, I'm so sorry.
我太害怕了   -别怕 我够稳
I'm very scared. -Okay. I got you.
别怕 深呼吸
It's okay. Breathe.
准备?   -好
Ready? Okay. -Yes.
莉莉!
Lily!
莉莉! 醒醒 醒醒
Lily, come on, come on.
醒醒 莉莉 醒醒
Come on. Lily, come on.
别这样 莉莉
Come on. Come on, Lily.
你在搞什么 法兰克
What is the matter with you, Frank?
你醒来了  -怎么可以丢下我一个人
You're alive! -How could you leave me?
我没有丢下你一个人 是因为好多鱼...
I didn't leave you. There was a lot of fish down there that...
鱼?什么鬼 法兰克
What? Fish? Frank...
很多食人鱼正朝我们冲过来
There were lot of piranha, they were coming after...
我为了救你，看我的衣服...   -不准看我
I saved you. Look.  -Don't even look at me.
好
Fine.
"化水为石"
"Turn water to stone..."
过了400年...
After 400 years...
我找到了
I found it.
我们找到了!
We found it!
你现在是花界达尔文了
Now you can be the Darwin of flowers.
花瓣在那 你自由了 你可以..
The petal's right there, you can be free. You can...
我意思是 河流很美
I mean, it's not like the river's not beautiful,
但你可以去更美的地方了
but you can go anywhere
环游世界 来伦敦
and you can see the world. You can come to London.
我住伦敦 可以带你参观
I'm from London. I could show it to you.
我有车子 我可以当你的船长
I even have a motor car. I could be like your skipper,
喘长...如果你喜欢的话
Skippy... If you want.
莉莉 我很喜欢和你在一起
Lily, I would love to do all that with you.
但我已经下定决心了
But I've made up my mind.
我没办法去伦敦
There is no London for me after this.
也没有汽车等着我
There's no motor car.
我已经准备好了
I'm ready.
不
No.
我的时候到了，该面对的总该是要面对的
It's my time. It was my time long ago.
不要 我不同意 你可以有新的人生的
No. No, I don't accept it. You could have one more life.
还好有选择权的人是我
Luckily for me, it's my choice.
有什么好开心的 你总是做出错误的决定
Well, it shouldn't be, because you have very poor judgement.
你还有大好人生在等着，那是你的世界
But you have your world to go back to. It's your world.
那也可以是你的世界啊
But it could be yours, too.
也许你的世界有某个人足矣
It could be that one person's world enough.
也许吧
Could be.
莉莉...
Lily...
莉莉
Lily.
哈啰
Hello.
我绝不会透露任何消息给一个用加农炮对着我的人
Small chance I told a madman with a cannon where to find you.
终于见面了
Oh, so, we finally meet.
哇 又大又壮的男孩 哈
Wow. Big, strong boy, huh?
去驾驶室 马上
Go to the bridge. Go.
这是你的吧?
I believe this belongs to you.
圣镞呢?
Now, the Arrowhead, please?
不 不 不
No, no, no.
真是一位想像力丰富的女人
Such an imaginative woman
死命寻找月亮之泪然后无私分享给科学界
seeking the Tears of the Moon to share with the scientific community
他们根本就不会给你一席之地
that won't even permit you, Fraulein, to sit among them.
把这种强大的力量
To put that tremendous power
交给一群乌合之众太浪费
into the hands of the masses would be pure madness.
交给我，不但可以帮德国打胜仗
When I could use the Tears, not only to win the war,
还能统治世世代代
but to reign for all generations to come.
带走
Take them away.
启动，朝向神树
Eyes ahead. Navigate to the Tree.
这棵树已经死了
This Tree is long dead.
你比谁都了解神树，所以..
You know more about the Tears of the Moon than anyone, so...
你会知道如何让树开花的，交给你了
you know how to make it bloom. You will do this for me.
你获得你想要的东西后
And when you have what you want,
也没理由让我们活着了吧
what's to stop you from killing us then?
我也可以现在就杀了你
I could kill you now.
我来
I'll do it.
但你要保证放他们离开，并留给我一片花瓣
If you promise to let them go and give me one single petal in return.
我对传说的所有细节了若指掌
I know the myths and the ancient ways as if I've lived them myself.
法兰克 别这样...
Frank, do not...
如果这里有谁能够拿到月亮之泪，那一定是我
If anyone here is going to bring the Tears of the Moon, it's me.
你让树开花，就给你花瓣
If you can make the Tree bloom, you may have your petal.
我保证
You have my word.
没别的办法了
There's no other way.
但小弟弟得留下
But the little brother stays on the boat.
小弟弟? 我有名字的
Little brother? I have a name.
去吧
Go ahead.
应该摆这吧
The Arrowhead should fit here.
去帮他一下   -不要
You better go help him. Go. -No.
不要?
No?
你也得给我一片花瓣
I'll do it if you give me a petal as well.
如果我也给你...
If I give you a petal as well...
只能留下一片，你们自己选
One petal. Not two. You must choose.
大只佬 你怎么想
What do you think, Muscles?
你愿意牺牲自己的花瓣给她?
Will you sacrifice your petal for her?
那她得先踏过我的尸体
She'd have to kill me first.
看着办   -没事啦
Done.  -Done.
"伤心的战士......"
"Broken-hearted warrior"
"爬上最高的山"
"climbed to the highest peak"
"向月亮射出他的箭"
"and shot his arrow into the Moon."
"月亮见他痛苦，也落下眼泪"
"From there, the Moon learned real pain and began to weep."
"眼泪落下之处一棵神圣的树发芽了"
"Where the Tears fell grew a sacred Tree..."
Rum-pum-pum-pum...
给我镞头
Give me the Arrow.
动作快!
Hurry up!
山姆说我必须修复破碎的心
Trader Sam said we would need to fix a broken heart.
这不是箭镞 而是一颗心
It's not an Arrowhead, it's a heart.
你无法修补一颗
You can't mend a heart that isn't...
没有破碎的心
...broken.
花瓣是我的了
I'll take that petal now.
"在哭泣的月亮下"
"Under the crying Moon..."
得在凋谢前赶紧采摘，快点儿!
We must pluck the petals before it sets. Go! Hurry!
又来
Every time.
抱歉
Sorry.
开枪!
Shoot!
干的好 杀人小猫咪
Good murder cat.
莉莉呢?
Where's Lily?
上面
Up there.
又来了
Here we go again.
月亮躲起来了
The Moon's setting.
树也开始凋零
The Tree is dying.
哇
Whoa.
加油
Come on.
太好了
Yes!
莉莉!
Lily!
这情况似曾相似呢?
This is a amusingly familiar situation, no?
给我花瓣
Give me that petal.
不   -你迟早要死
No. -You are about to die one way or another,
但是不交给我
but if you do not give me that petal,
你弟可就不一定能活着了
so, too, will your brother.
我会让他慢慢被折磨到死
His will be much more slower.
给我花瓣!
Give me that petal.
一片就好 给我!
Just one is enough. Give it to me.
死都不要，法兰克!
Never. Frank!
放开我!
Let go of me!
掌好舵
Take the wheel. Hold her steady.
你是我养过最棒的猫咪
You're the best cat I've ever had.
滚开
Get off!
看来你对我的小蜜蜂们
It looks like you haven't been very nice...
不太友善
to my little friends.
阿吉雷 去抢花瓣
Aguirre, help me to get the petal!
拿到花瓣，我给你一切，钱，船
I'll give you anything you want! Money, ships...
整个西班牙王国!
Spain!
皇室不值得信任
Royalty is not to be trusted.
阿吉雷，那个穿长裤的女人...
Aguirre, the woman in pants...
拦住她!
Get her!
阿吉雷!
Aguirre!
法兰西斯科拿到花瓣了
Francisco has the petal!
阻止他!
Stop him!
你的终点站到了  -什么?
This is where you get off. -What?
告诉莉莉，她就是我的全世界
Tell Lily she would've been world enough for me.
你要去哪?
Where are you going?
普西玛，保护好他，你是自己的主人了 去吧
Proxima. You protect him, you're in charge. Go.
再见 小猫
Goodbye, girl.
让我们进行最后一次航行吧
Let's give 'em one last cruise, mi buena nina.
只有一个方法能结束这一切
There's only one way to end this.
来抓我!
Come and get me.
莉莉
Lily.
他要撞墙了
He's going to crash.
不，他是想堵住河水
No, he's gonna block the river.
法兰西斯科!
Francisco!
花瓣给我!
Give me the petal!
在他口袋!
He has the petal in his pocket!
我受够了
Enough is enough!
我要杀了你们两个!
It's now time for you to die!
好
Right.
我想我们已经受够了你
I think we've had quite enough of you.
晚安
Good night.
我不是故意的...
Not exactly what I intended.
兄弟之情伤人最深
A brother's blade cuts deepest.
给我花瓣
Give me the petal.
他告诉我要告诉你
He told me to tell you,
你就是他的全世界
you would have been world enough for him.
花瓣在哪?
Where's the petal?
抱歉了 老朋友
I'm sorry, old friend.
他把这个留给了你
He wanted you to have it.
拦下船!  拦下他!!
Stop the boat! Stop it!
法兰克  -等等
Frank. -Wait.
法兰克，不要!
Frank, no!
不可以!
No!
法兰西斯科，你做了什么?
Francisco, what have you done?
你把我折磨得比死还难受
This is worse than death! This is torture!
你真的让我又气又痛
Oh, you are the most infuriating man I've ever met.
莉莉
Lily...
法兰克
Frank.
法兰克!
Frank!
你在流血
Oh, you're bleeding.
好痛
That hurts.
会痛?    -对
It does? -Yeah.
那很好阿
Well, that's good.
你竟然真的对我开枪
I can't believe you shot me.
厉害吧   -还打两发?
I know.   -Twice.
我知道 但是你中了一枪不倒下
I know, but you didn't go down the first time.
你应该倒下的
You should've just gone down.
你们真是我的全世界
You're both my world.
哇 哇 哇
Well, well, well...
尼罗，整艘都是你的了
Nilo. Now you have all the boats.
好好照顾她
Take care of her.
我曾在同一个讲台上说起月亮之泪
I stand before you today to tell you about the Tears of the Moon.
这个传说是真的
The legend is true.
我们比其他任何人都更深入地进入亚马逊
Our party traveled further into the Amazon than any expedition had previously dared.
在这场旅程中，生死变得模糊
On our trip, the lines between life and death,
过去与现在之间的界限消失了
past and present, vanished.
我亲眼见证了传说化为现实
I witnessed things not to be believed.
见证可以迷惑心智的妖河豚
Enchanted dolphins that could haunt one's dreams.
见证丛林的囚犯
Undead conquistadors,
被诅咒的征服者
cursed as prisoners of the jungle for nearly 400 years.
一个部落酋长，一位女士
A tribe whose chief, a lady...
别嘘，他们运作的挺好的
No! It actually worked rather well.
重点是，这是一个
My point is, this was a journey
整个科学界从未体验过的旅程
the likes of which this society has never seen.
一次无愧这个冒险协会的冒险
An adventure truly worthy of this association.
但这协会值得我们这样冒险吗?
But is this association worthy of our great adventure?
其实，我们也不用去找月亮之泪
You see, we didn't seek the Tears of the Moon
随便用一堆屁话充篇幅
so that we could be written up in some journal
就能交出一篇期刊变会员啊
for a load of crusty old farts.
我的姐姐，现在是剑桥大学的教授
My sister, who just made full professor at Cambridge,
麻烦我，有礼貌地
has asked me to respectfully reject
帮她拒绝你们协会的会员邀请
your invitation of membership on her behalf.
拒绝没问题啊，但是我不会有礼貌
Which I will do. Just not respectfully.
先生们 请把邀请函
Gentlemen, you can take your invitation
塞进自己的屁股里
and you can shove it up your association.
小子岂敢!
How dare you!
准备好上课了吗?
Ready for your first driving lesson?
应该吧 裤子女士
I think so, Pants.
希望你明白等下要面对什么
I hope you know what you're getting yourself into here, Frank.
面对方向盘
A car.
喔 你的笑点
Oh, your jokes.
总有一天会要我命
They will be the death of me.
简直跟放屁..折磨人一样
They are absolutely exhausting.
哇 莉莉
Wow, Lily.
你喜欢?   -这好笑
Did you like it? -It was good.
没错   -有没有骄傲?
Yeah. -Are you proud?
噢 法兰克 法兰克 法兰克!
Oh! Frank, Frank, Frank!
喔我的天阿   -好 我会了
Oh, my goodness! -Okay, I got it.
法兰克 夭寿哦
Frank, for goodness' sake!
我会了 我会了    -转弯! 转弯! 马上转弯!!
I got it, I got it. Turn now! Turn now! Turn now!
安啦 裤子小姐
I got it all under control, Pants.